now you talk about terror
[Music]
what about for me
i've been terrorized
[Music]
all my days
welcome to the chris hedges report
the cia from its inception carried out
assassinations coups torture and illegal
spying and abuse including of u.s
citizens many of which were exposed in
1975 by the church committee in the
senate and the pike committee in the
house
congress attempted to enact laws to curb
the widespread criminal activity by the
cia
senate and house intelligence oversight
committees were created and after the
iran contra scandal a statutory
inspector general at the cia was
appointed but this oversight largely
collapsed following the attacks of 911
and the so-called war on terror
the activities of the cia have once
again reverted to the shadows
the cia at the same time has transformed
itself into a paramilitary organization
with its own armed units and drone
program the us allocates a secret black
budget of about 50 billion dollars a
year to hide multiple types of
clandestine projects carried out by the
national security agency the cia and
other intelligence agencies usually
beyond the scrutiny of congress
john kiriakou worked for the cia from
1990 to 2004 first as an analyst and
later as a counterterrorism operations
officer overseas in bahrain athens and
pakistan where he was the cia's chief of
counter-terrorist operations he led a
series of military raids on al-qaeda
safe houses in pakistan capturing dozens
of suspects including the 2002 raid that
captured abu zabeda then thought to be
the third ranking member of al-qaeda he
was also the first cia officer to
publicly confirm that the cia
waterboarded prisoners and that such an
action was torture
he confirmed that torture was an
official u.s government policy rather
than wrongdoing by a few rogue agents he
became the sixth whistleblower indicted
under the espionage act by the obama
administration and was sent to prison
for two and a half years
joining me to discuss the cia how it has
evolved how it sees its mission what it
does how it works and the effects of its
clandestine operations around the globe
is john kiriako
so john
in theory the cia is subject to
oversight by congress and uh the
inspector general throughout
the intelligence community but this
oversight has been weakened almost to
the point of non-existence and i
wondered if you could talk about
uh the nature of the oversight and the
consequences of
the lack of oversight
sure chris first of all thanks for
having me uh you're right about
oversight oversight was a very serious
thing uh beginning in 1975
and it was certainly serious uh through
the reagan administration into the end
of the
1980s there were members of the senate
select committee on intelligence and the
house permanent select committee on
intelligence that took their oversight
duties very very seriously
and uh that uh that began to to weaken
in in the 90s and then it changed
utterly
when when the 9 11 attacks took place uh
now we've got these oversight committees
that really act as little more than
cheerleaders for the cia you know it's
up to these these members of congress to
tell the cia
no you can't do that no you can't have a
torture program or an illegal rendition
program or an archipelago of secret
prisons around the world you can't
transform yourself without congressional
approval into a paramilitary
organization uh you can't set up an
assassination squad that travels around
the world to just carry out hits of
people whose politics you don't like
and we just don't get that kind of
oversight anymore
we had the feinstein report and the ci
really effectively railroaded her didn't
they oh yeah they did
you'll recall too that john brennan when
he was the cia director as that report
was being researched and written ordered
cia officers or cia contractors it's
never really been clear to hack into the
senate intelligence committee's computer
system to see what it was that these
these investigators were gathering and
you know even though that was referred
to the justice department in a crimes
report there was never any investigation
and certainly never a prosecution well i
remember she was quite uh shaken by
feinstein by that oh yes and gave a kind
of very chilling
press conference that basically said uh
these people are unaccountable i i i
remember correctly
yeah you're exactly right in fact
dianne feinstein had a reputation as
being one of the most pro-cia members of
the u.s senate and for her to go onto
the floor of the senate and accuse in
very plain english the cia director of
committing a crime a felony
was a very big deal it was a turning
point for her and and what are so what
are the consequences of essentially
removing this kind of oversight
yeah the the consequences of removing
real oversight true oversight is you end
up with a rogue organization the nature
of the cia is to push the envelope the
nature is to to see what it is that they
can get away with um on the one hand on
the other hand the nature is to try to
recruit these members of the oversight
committees to make them feel like
they're one of the guys they're they're
part of this secret team they're
insiders they're all everybody's working
together and that way you can get away
with things that you otherwise
wouldn't get away with or or wouldn't
attempt well that's not what the role of
an oversight committee is supposed to be
the role of the oversight committee is
to say no
to say you can't do that because it's
illegal and the committee just doesn't
do things like that i'll give you one
example
when i got
home from prison
i was invited to a reception and there
was a democratic senator at this at this
party he was a member of the uh
of the senate intelligence committee and
uh he was not really happy to see me and
i was perfectly happy making him feel
uncomfortable so i walked right up to
him and he said hello and i said hello
senator and i knew him from when i was
on the senate foreign relations
committee staff i said senator i got to
tell you i'm i'm disappointed uh that uh
you know i couldn't count on your
support when all of this went down and
he got very angry and he said look
it takes all my energy just to not lose
my security clearance
and man that made it completely clear to
me
that they're afraid of oversight
they're afraid of being threatened by
the cia they're afraid of losing their
security clearances
and so
they they carry out this charade
where they pretend to conduct oversight
and then really behind closed doors they
just do what the cia tells them to do
that's what it's come down to i just
have to go a little off topic because i
thought you might know and it's always
fascinated me why they took down
petraeus
because it appears he was clearly taken
down
yeah
you know i've i've gone over this in in
my head many many times um petraeus was
not
a political figure um
and i'll tell you there's there's kind
of a history at the cia
of
having weak directors who used to be
generals or admirals
and the way it was always told to me was
you don't want a military man in a
position like that because military
people have have gotten where they have
gotten with four shiny stars on their
shoulders by saying yes sir for the
previous 30 or 35 years
and you don't want somebody to say yes
sir you want somebody to say mr
president
let me tell you what it is we want to do
and why we want to do it
where you're telling the president
what intelligence policy is going to be
and generals and admirals normally don't
do things like that they don't stand up
to presidents
and i always wondered if if that plus
the fact that he was just not a
political player
was what eventually did him in
well having spent a lot of time in the
military i found the iq levels
diminished the higher you went up
isn't that
the cia functions as both
an intelligence gathering
organization and an organization that
carries out operations
and i wondered how this dual focus
affects the kinds of intelligence
it gathers
yeah good question you know before 9 11
the whole purpose of operations was to
gather intelligence you implemented an
operation because it was going to
provide you with a new line of
information because the job of a cia
officer is to recruit spies to steal
secrets and then you pass those secrets
to the analysts so that they can provide
the best possible analysis to the policy
makers to make the best possible policy
in a perfect world that's
that's why the cia exists but that
changed after 9 11. so you've got
you've got a handful of analysts now
whose job it is to recruit spies to
steal secrets to influence policy
and then most of the directorate of
operations
to do counter terrorism counter
narcotics counter proliferation uh to go
out there you know shooting people up or
snatching people off the streets to
render them to to third countries it's
it's just a completely different place
you mentioned in your intro that the cia
is now a paramilitary organization i've
been making that complaint for many many
years that's exactly what it is it's a
paramilitary organization and so the
people that the cia is hiring now the
people
you know most of us used to be hired
right out of graduate school
because we had advanced degrees from
good schools and we spoke foreign
languages that's really not who they're
looking for anymore they're looking for
people who were navy seals green berets
you know special operations forces they
they maybe did a rotation of the cia on
uh on loan from special operations
command you're looking for people who
can jump out of planes rough it in the
jungle or the desert kill people and
then exfiltrate themselves so the cia
really has changed quite dramatically
since 9 11. so i'm wondering if there
isn't a danger that intelligence gets
distorted and contaminated
to justify operations
oh very very much so you know the night
that we captured abu zabeda that was
that was
obviously the biggest night of my career
and it was one of the most important
nights of of my life to tell you the
truth not just because of the excitement
of capturing someone that we had hunted
for for six weeks um
and this is going to sound kind of silly
but what i was the most excited about
was in the abu zabeta raid we had um
captured
uh confiscated
a copy of the al-qaeda training manual
in
a safe house that was occupied by three
members of the lashkar lashkar-e-tayaba
pakistani militant group terrorist group
this was the very first time that we
were able to tie
lashkar-e-tayaba to al-qaeda
so analytically this was a gigantic leap
forward in our understanding of how
terrorist groups worked
i was the only person who cared
nobody cared all they wanted to know
was who we caught
and who they were with when we caught
them that was it now the analysts were
very very excited because this answered
so many questions where was lashkar
tayaba getting their their weapons and
ammunition who was funding them we
always feared it was isi it turned out
it wasn't diocy it turned out it was al
qaeda but how did they make the
connection what was the the rat line
between the two organizations the
analysts were fascinated by this but in
the directorate of operations nobody
cared so there was this move away from
analysis there was a move away from
understanding the enemy
and the goal really was to just kill or
capture and then move on to the next
target
so the national security act 1947 that
established the cia
defined its function as combining
compiling and analyzing raw intelligence
to make it useful to the president the
cia reports to the president
it was supposed to be civilian
nonpartisan free from the vested
interests of the military-industrial
complex can you explain how
it evolved into what's become the
executive branch's private army oh yeah
you know when i first started at the cia
i was told what you just read
uh nonpartisan in all capital letters i
sat near a woman
in 1995 1996 who had a bob dole for
president bumper sticker very discreetly
in her cubicle and not only was she
ordered to take it down
but uh but she was reprimanded for
bringing politics into the office
i sat next to people for years
and never had the foggiest idea if they
were democrats or republicans or
independents or whatever they were it
was never raised it was never important
because we had the mission
and you know i don't mean to keep coming
back to 911 but
on the day that 9 11 that the attacks
took place
everything changed
everything
and so it became
you know it really did become the
president's private army i i remember i
remember uh executive order one two
three three three being written in stone
it was one of the very first things we
were briefed on when we were hired into
the agency that we cannot kill people we
do not and will not kill people and we
will not task others with killing people
well within just days of the 911 attacks
one two three three three was um
was rescinded
and all of a sudden we started setting
up
uh assassination squads when i was in
the cia's counter-terrorism center i sat
i don't know 20 feet away from a guy
who was very friendly
he would come in and say good morning
every day morning guys i'd say good
morning morning rick how are you doing
how was your weekend how are your kids
and then he would disappear for a week
two weeks at a time and we just all
assumed he was going tdy temporary duty
like we all did i made 25 international
trips in in the one year after the 9 11
attacks
and then finally one day i said to the
guy i sat next to
what exactly does he do here
like he's i see him all the time he's
very friendly
but i don't really know what he does
and my friend was kind of exasperated he
said john
he's in charge of the special activities
division you get it
special activities and i said uh of
course
so he would he would just get on a plane
go to some foreign country
kill people get back on the plane and
come home and just wait for the next
assignment i had um i had worked in the
middle east for a little while with uh
with a contractor an old timer legendary
figure by the name of billy wah
uh books have been written about billy
he's such a legendary figure in the
korean war the vietnam war uh the guy
had been around for for decades and um
and then he just kind of dropped out of
sight
so i ran into him in the hall about six
weeks after 9 11
and i said hey billy haven't seen you in
ages where have you been and he looked
around and he said he whispered to me
i've been in afghanistan
i said yeah what are you doing in
afghanistan
and he looked at me like i was crazy he
said i've been killing people what do
you think i've been doing and see i had
been volunteering to go to afghanistan
repeatedly like every few days i'd go
into the deputy director of
counterterrorism uh the
counter-terrorism center's office saying
i really want to go to afghanistan you
have to send me to afghanistan my arabic
is fluent and i'm thinking who do they
have i mean there are only half a dozen
of us that spoke arabic who did they
have doing these interrogations well it
was that conversation in the hall that
made me realize they're not
interrogating anybody they're just
killing them
so they didn't need linguists and former
analysts like me they needed people who
could pull a trigger have zero remorse
and then go to the next target and pull
the trigger there too so after 9 11 i
was based in paris covering al qaeda
in europe and north africa
and i worked a lot with french
intelligence i'm only going to repeating
what they said
um
i i having spent 20 years abroad i can
tell you once an intelligence service
resorts to torture its intelligence
functioning has broken down uh that's
what you do as a last resort uh the
french argued that they were the only
intelligence service that had human
assets inside of al-qaeda uh and that
the united states uh was completely
blind that it relied primarily on
electronic eavesdropping um but didn't
had not built up the kind of human
capital that the french uh had built up
uh and therefore really didn't know what
was going on i don't know if that's a
critique you would agree with
yes i would agree with that uh utterly i
i have a passage in my first book uh
where
i talk about a a team of
of middle eastern intelligence officers
who came to head to headquarters cia
headquarters on july the 7th
2001. this was a completely normal
routine visit where
they come for a day we exchange gifts we
give them a day of briefings they get a
photo op with the director i take them
to morton's steakhouse at the end of the
day and then we do it with somebody else
the next day
so
july the 7th i set up a series of
briefings and one of the briefings for
them was uh was on al qaeda it was
supposed to be conducted by a junior
analyst and much to my shock
into the briefing walks kopher black
later ambassador for black the director
of the cia's counter-terrorism center
and um
and a woman we used to call the
red-headed devil i i won't
i ought not to say her name but she was
the chief of operations in the osama bin
laden group and um
i said oh welcome i i was so surprised i
said to these middle easterners
gentlemen this is uh
ko for black he's the director of the
counter-terrorism center and kopher sat
down and and cut right to the chase and
he said something terrible is going to
happen we don't know when we don't know
where but we know it's going to be huge
uh we're picking up chatter where
where al qaeda's camp commanders are on
the phone with their students and and
they're crying and saying i'll see you
in paradise
we're hearing code words for a major
attack uh there's going to be a great
soccer match there's going to be a huge
wedding uh this the honey salesman is
coming with vast quantities of honey
these are all codes for a major attack
and he said i beg you if you have any
sources inside al qaeda please help us
so afterwards at the end of the day i
sent these guys back to their hotel
before the dinner and i went to cover's
office to thank him for taking the time
and i said kopher i i've got to ask you
because i wasn't working on al qaeda at
the time i said
was that for their benefit or were you
serious and he said oh no i was serious
he said we don't have any sources inside
al qaeda and we know that something
terrible is coming i covered the war in
kosovo and made the first trip with
members of the kosovo liberation army
and then met with wes clark afterwards
who was the head of nato
and he was asking me what kind of
weapons they had and how many there were
and he slammed his hand down on the desk
and he said langley doesn't have anybody
on the ground
nope
nope that's quite common and they rely
far far too much on electronic
eavesdropping you know you can't have
nsa do all of your work for you
that that's not that's not a full
complement of intelligence
so
frank church this is after going through
the heavily redacted cia documents that
were provided the church committee in 75
this is how he defines covert activity
quote
a semantic disguise for murder coercion
blackmail bribery the spreading of lies
and consorting with known torturers and
international terrorists is that
accurate
unfortunately yes that is that is
accurate you know i i've got to give
credit to to bill clinton um in this
question because when bill clinton was
elected president
you remember the the 1992 election it
was all about the economy stupid
remember
so uh bill clinton really had very very
little interest in uh in the cia and in
foreign policy foreign policy just was
not his thing and you know we were used
to briefing the president every single
day six days a week with the president's
daily brief george h.w bush had been the
cia director he had been ambassador to
the u.n ambassador to china and he
relished these briefings and even ronald
reagan even as he became you know dim in
the last two years of his presidency he
got the briefing six days a week well
bill clinton was briefed twice
over the course of his eight-year
presidency he just was not interested al
gore was interested but clinton wasn't
well the one thing that bill clinton did
at the very start of his presidency was
he initiated something called a call
so he ordered the cia to
to identify every recruited asset who
had some sort of a human rights problem
in his background and to fire that
source right throw him off the payroll
no more meetings no more talking we're
not dealing with human rights violators
and
i remember my bosses laughing
in the beginning like this is never ever
going to work and sure enough
fully one-third of the cia's recruited
assets were fired in that call
and for all those eight years of the
clinton presidency
there really was respect for human
rights it was something that nobody
thought would work
it actually did work
but then and i hate to keep repeating
myself
911 hit
and then all the rules just went right
out the window
so i want to talk about blowback uh uh
afghanistan you know being perhaps the
[Music]
prime example of that 1979 when we were
supporting
the mujahideen uh later became the
taliban
um
richard clark argues i'm quoting again
the cia used its classification rules
not only to protect its agents but also
to deflect outside scrutiny of its
covert operations peter thompson
the former ambassador to the afghan
resistance during the 80s
said that quote america's failed
policies in afghanistan flowed in part
from the uh compartmented top secret
isolation in which the cia always sought
to work uh i was in the balkans when the
cia was kidnapping
all sorts of mujahideen many of them
were from egypt they were sent on black
flights back to egypt i think almost all
of them
were killed uh and then we saw of course
the u.s embassy bombings in kenya and
tanzania 98 that was 224
dead
the attack on the us's coal to most
americans that came out of nowhere to
those of us who were overseas
uh
we we saw this as blowback can you talk
about that phenomena
yeah this this
was truly blowback
uh blowback is is essentially an
unintended consequence but really what
it is is the consequence of poor
planning and poor execution you know the
cia one of the things that the cia is is
always guilty of is
is poor planning
uh it was drilled into us as soon as
as soon as we went into operations that
you have to have a plan and then you
have to have a plan b c and d and that's
great when you're sitting in a
conference room or you know writing it
in a report but it's it's just not
really the way things work in real life
and
even if you do have a plan b c and d
that's not necessarily to say that the
policymakers do
and that uh that they're going to
do something that you think is the right
thing to do afghanistan is probably
the worst uh example of blowback in our
modern history
where
you know we had this obsession with
communism i think most americans don't
understand really the governments and
the cia's obsession with communism
right up until the end
the end of communism uh in europe and so
in this obsession with communism
and this this willingness
or readiness to drive out the soviets
and drive them out of afghanistan at all
costs
we made a deal with the devil
and then when the russians were finally
driven out of afghanistan rather than to
try to
work with a new afghan government
you know to
to
enhance infrastructure or agriculture or
education
we just walked away
it was as simple as that
there was no plan b
or
the plan ended with the defeat of the
soviet union in afghanistan and so here
here we've radicalized these people
we've pumped hundreds of millions
probably billions of dollars
worth of
of weapons and ammunition and mines and
rockets and you name it uh into this
country
and then we just abandoned them
so uh
there there should have been no surprise
when they morphed into the taliban with
the help of the pakistani government and
the pakistani intelligence service the
isi like what did we think was going to
happen
and then by the time
you know 9 11 happened it was
it was just too late
i want a central senator daniel patrick
moynihan argued that
the agency should be dismantled
because as he wrote it produced
catastrophically wrong national
intelligence estimates including of
course failing to predict the father
shaw collapse of the soviet union
uh
throughout the reagan and bush
administration overstated the size of
the soviet economy by at least 50
percent
uh it led the government on a weapon
spending spree that left us the world's
largest debtor nation
uh and then of course we have the
disastrous intelligence on iraq and
non-existence of weapons of mass
description
i wonder if
do we need a cia that so regularly
underperforms
in comparison to what's often available
from scholars and journalists
and if we do what should be done to
reform the cia
i i feel very strongly that we do not
need a cia i think that if we ever did
need a cia it's long overstate it's uh
it's welcome uh and you look at
redundancy and intelligence around the
us government too chris
you've got the state department's bureau
of intelligence and research which does
uh
all
kinds of of intelligence analysis
uh you've got the defense department's
dhs defense human services
they recruit spies to steal secrets just
like the cia does
you have nsa uh doing all of the
electronic eavesdropping you have darpa
developing the next generation of
whatever it is that they do it's so
secret we don't even know what what it
is that they're working on uh we've got
think tanks uh most of which are funded
and financed by the big defense
contractors
we don't we don't need a cia and to tell
you the truth there's a there's a major
book waiting to be written on the cia's
analytic failures you know we talk all
the time about the cia's operational
failures those are very well documented
legacy of ashes is one of the best books
i've ever read
but what we don't talk about is the
cia's analytic failures and if you go
back really to the founding of the cia
in 1947
they've either missed or gotten
gotten the analysis wrong on every major
event i mean we can go back to
the suez crisis we can go back to the
berlin airlift
uh through uh the iraq war and
everything that came after they they're
wrong about everything
and and there's never a price to pay for
that they just move on to the next
crisis and and then get that wrong well
my favorite obsession is
they trot out what the cardinal in
prague
uh who's been uh of course worked over
to say what the communist regime wants
him to say and everybody in the cia
thinks that the soviets have figured out
the drugs for mind control uh which
sends them off on you know dropping even
to their own agents giving them lsd tabs
some of them jump out of hotel windows
and kill themselves um steve kinser
wrote a good book on this called
poisoner in chief uh but i think that's
what comes when there's no
accountability and also the kinds of
figures dulles you know
these are uh
very problematic
people
oh problematic people who do not have
the country's best interests at heart
dulles is probably the best uh example
of this
dulles
dulles saw the cia as his own fiefdom
and what president eisenhower wanted
from him was immaterial
uh he and his brother colluded and
conspired on on myriad operations and
foreign policy issues and they didn't
care what eisenhower had to say about it
well they were just gangsters for wall
street weren't they that's exactly what
they were yeah yes
so i have to ask this question since i
know oliver stone he's convinced the cia
killed jfk i've never seen that so is
david talbott and others i i've never
seen any evidence that backs it up but
what do you think
um oliver once
yelled at me that i was full of [__]
because i said that uh i said i don't
know oliver i just can't wrap my brain
around it i i i hope not i hope you're
wrong i said i i haven't seen any
evidence of it it's certainly an
interesting story but i said you know
maybe maybe you should look at the santo
trafficante and the role of the mafia in
the death of kennedy and then he
exploded you're so full of [__]
so i i never i've never bought it but uh
i was curious what you thought all right
i want to thank the real news network
and its production team cameron
grenadino adam coley dwayne gladden and
kayla rivera you can find me at
chrishedges.substance.com
[Music]
you